Principal's Office
The discipline at this school has been lacking lately.
（校長先生）最近 校内の
風紀が乱れてきてましてな
Nichijou 14
I'd like you to be a little more strict on keeping students to the school rules, Sakurai-sensei.
生徒指導の桜井(さくらい)先生には―
もう少し 厳しく
取り締まっていただきたいと
（桜井先生）はい
Yes!
I-I'll do my best!
が… 頑張ります
That's right, I became a student guidance counsellor in order to change myself!
（桜井）そうだ
私は私を変えるために
生徒指導の先生に
なったんだもん
I'll have to make sure that they stick to the rules.
しっかり 取り締まらなきゃ
うにゃあん！
What's this?
（桜井）なんてこった
いきなり なんてこった
What's this, all of a sudden?!
But it's not good, since it's only allowed during lunchtime.
でもダメ
ひるんじゃダメなんだから
（桜井）あ… あの
E-Excuse me!
What seems to be the problem, Miss?
（笹原幸治郎(ささはらこうじろう)）
どうなされた？ 御仁
ああ すみません
ええっとですね
Sorry, um... I don't think it's good manners to eat while walking...
歩きながら食べるのは
少し行儀が悪いかな… なんて
ハッハッハッ　失敬
How rude of me.
My stomach wouldn't stop growling,
朝食を抜いたせいか
腹のやつが 急に いななきおってな
most likely because I didn't eat breakfast.
I'll take it off now, sorry about that.
今すぐ下げよう　失礼であった
S-Sorry.
す… すみません　いいんです
分かってもらえれば それで
It's okay!
As long as you understand, it's...
（桜井）よかった
言えば分かってくれるんだな
I'm glad that he understands it when I tell him.
Tell them...
（笹原）伝えてくれ
（桜井）あ…
...that it was delicious!
美味であったと！
What do you mean, "delicious"?!
（立花(たちばな)みさと）
何が美味よ　廊下で大声出して！
Suddenly shouting in the middle of the hallway?!
You should think about your surroundings for a bit!
少しは風紀 考えたらどうなのよ
U-Um, you can't take something like that to school...
あ… あの それは
学校に持ってきては
（ウェボシー）みさと　行くよ
Misato, let's go.
Ah, okay.
Sasahara, I have something to talk to you about during lunch, so...
笹原　あんたは昼休み話があるから
教室にいなさいよ
...be in the classroom then!
This school might really be lacking discipline.
（桜井）確かに 風紀が
乱れているのかもしれない
That was rude.
（笹原）失敬
（桜井）あっ
Tachibana Misato didn't mean any harm either.
立花みさとも
悪気があったわけではないのだ
許してくれ
Please forgive her.
Ah, yes.
あっ はい　すみませんでした
Sorry about that.
（桜井）あっ あの
（笹原）ああ？
E-Excuse me!
What is that?
それ 何ですか？
その首のフリフリの
That frilly thing around your neck...
Ah, this?
ああ これか？
Yes.
（桜井）
はい　なんか カワイイなって
I was thinking it's kinda cute.
The ordinary days that we have been living might actually be a chain of miracles.
日々 私たちが過ごしている
日常というのは―
実は奇跡の連続なのかもしれん
As it were, it might be something like that.
いわば―
そういうものかもしれんな
Ah, hm, so in other words, what is that frilly thing...
（桜井）ああっ えっと つまり
そのフリフリは何なんでしょう？
It's ****, I say.
ぬかしおる
Well then, Miss, we shall meet again in class.
では 御仁
機会があったら授業で
Hmm...
ああっ  ウフッ
Thank you... very much.
ありがとうございました
Wanna try it?
（女子生徒Ａ）帰りに寄ってみる？
（女子生徒Ｂ）うん　楽しそうね
Sure, it looks fun.
Student Guidance
Excuse me, Nakanojou-kun!
（桜井）すみません 中之条(なかのじょう)君！
（中之条 剛(つよし)）うん？ あっ
Yes, what is it?
はい　何でしょうか？
Ah, nothing really. Just you know...
あっ いえ　あの ですね
学校で その髪型は
ちょっと あれかな？ なんて
I was thinking that having a hairstyle like yours at school is a little...
Ah no, only a little, just a little...
ああ いえ ちょっとだけ…
ちょっとだけかな？ なんて
...It won't...
（中之条）…こないんです
（桜井）あっ
Ah, I'm sorry.
あっ ごめんなさい
I didn't quite hear that, can you say it once more...
ちょっと聞こえなかったから
もう一度
From the sides...
（中之条）横から…
It won't grow from the sides!
横から生えてこないんです！
Go Soccer Club 1
Daruma-san has...
（大工健三郎(だいくけんざぶろう)）
だーるーまーさーんーが
...tumbled down!
ころんだ！
Everyone went home.
（関口(せきぐち)ユリア）
みんな 帰りました
Please take another 1000 steps forward
Nichijou 15
Nano, what are these?
（はかせ）なの  これ何？
TL note: Ume is an Asian fruit, otherwise known as the Japanese apricot or Chinese plum.
They're unripe ume.
（東雲(しののめ)なの）青梅ですよ
TL note: Umeboshi is pickled ume that's often added to onigiri (Japanese rice balls).
I've been thinking of making some umeboshi at home this year.
今年は家で 梅干し漬けて
みようかなって思ってるんです
Umeboshi... sour.
梅干し しゅっぱい
Ume are good for your health, you know.
梅は体にいいんですよ
Besides, if you put it in your onigiri, the rice won't spoil.
それに おにぎりに入れておくと
ご飯が悪くならないし
ジャーン！
うわあっ　なの！
Nano!
You can't!
（なの）ダメです
（はかせ）ガン！
I haven't even said anything yet.
はかせ まだ
何も言ってないんだけど
お菓子は この前 いっぱい
買ったばかりじゃないですか
We just bought a lot of snacks recently, haven't we?
We'll finish those first, and then we can go buy more again...
まず それをちゃんと食べて
なくなったら また買いに
（はかせ）わあっ
Oh geez, Professor...
ああ もう　はかせ！
You can't have those today. That cat...
ダメですよ
今日は あの猫さん…
Um...
えーと
阪本(さかもと)
Sakamoto.
Ah yeah, we also promised to buy Sakamoto-san's food,
あっ そう
阪本さんのごはんも―
買っていくって
約束してるんですから
so snacks are...
お菓子は…
Pocky.
大きい
（なの）あっ あの
Ah, um...
Yes?
（店員）
はい　何かご用でしょうか？
Can I help you with anything?
Ah, this, this is...
こ… この これは？
Ah, the snowman? It just came in today.
ああ 雪だるまですね
本日入荷しました
If you want, you're welcome to buy it.
よろしかったら どうぞ
Is it a snack?
お菓子？
Ah, maybe it's something like shaved ice.
（なの）あっ アイスの
かき氷みたいな物でしょうか
It's cold.
冷たい
安い
It's cheap!
You're gonna buy it?
（はかせ）買うの？
（なの）え？
N-No, I'm only taking a look.
い… いや 見てただけです
（男性）ああっ 雪だるまじゃん
Ah, a snowman!
I want it.
（女性）私 欲しい
Hey you.
（おばさん）ちょっと あんた
あっ はい
Y-Yes?
If you're not going to buy it, can you give it to me?
それ 買わないんだったら
こっちにちょうだいよ
I-I'm buying it!
か… 買います！
（はかせ）あーあ
なのは なのの買うのに―
Why can Nano buy the things Nano wants,
はかせは はかせの
買っちゃダメって言う
but Professor can't buy the things Professor wants?
No, as I said, this is just...
（なの）いえ ですからこれは
（はかせ）うう…
Since Nano is buying the things Nano wants,
なのは なのの買うんだから―
はかせも はかせの
買ってもいいし！
it's okay for Professor to buy the things Professor wants too!
I want it, I want it, I really want it, I want it!
（はかせ）欲しい 欲しい
（なの）うーん
（はかせ）
欲しいったら欲しい！
I got it.
分かりました　１個だけですよ
Just one pack, okay?
Really?
ホント？ へへっ
Nano, I love you.
なの 好き
So that's how you ended up buying that thing?
（阪本）それでそんなもん
買ってきたっていうのか
Yes, it's cute, and since it's cold, it feels good.
はい　カワイイし
冷たくて気持ちもいいし
（阪本）ふーん
Professor, it's done.
はかせ　できましたよ
Yes!
（はかせ）はーい　ヘヘヘ
うーんと
Nano, gimme more!
なの もっと！
Yes, yes.
Seriously, you guys...
（阪本）まったく お前らは
And where's my food?
それで 俺のメシはどこだ？
Ah!
Shaved ice?
かき氷
They want me to eat... shaved ice?
こんなメシは―
こーりごり なんてな
First comes rock, next comes paper, rockscispaper doesn't count,
（はかせ･なの）
♪ 最初はグー その次パー
rock-paper-scissors!
It's going up~
（はかせ）上へ参りまーす
ネジが！
The screw!
Nichijou 16
Midterm Test
Health
English
（長野原(ながのはら)みお）うーん
（相生祐子(あいおいゆうこ)）あっ ああ…
TL note: This is a reference to the painting "The Creation of Adam", by Michelangelo, on the ceiling of the Sistine Chapel.
だああ！
（みお）フウッ
No no.
（祐子）ＮＯＮＯ(ノノ)
（水上麻衣(みなかみまい)）フッ
Okay, the test is over.
あっ はい　テスト終了です
Good heavens!
（祐子）ナムサーン！
This is a wig too.
（麻衣）これもヅラ
Word Of The Day
When you think of what other people are looking for,
you might not know because there are so many other people.
When you think of what you're looking for,
isn't it a little bit of love?
After that, you've just got to pray to a god somewhere.
Well then,
a god somewhere, pleased to meet you.
Go Soccer Club 2
Daruma-san...
（大工）だーるーまーさ…
...has tumbled down!
んが ころんだ！
Maybe you should stop that already?
（ユリア）もう やめませんか？
A Parrot
ああ また 立たされた
They made me stand again.
I've adapted quite well to this body.
（インコ）
この体にも だいぶ慣れてきたぞ
（祐子）おわあ！
Nichijou 17
Just by looking at them, I can't stop drooling.
見てるだけで
ヨダレがたまってきますね
What's this?
（阪本）何だ これは？
Ah, Sakamoto-san.
あっ 阪本さん　梅干しですよ
It's umeboshi.
（阪本）ふーん
（なの）あっ
（阪本）ニョイヨ！
You can't eat them, because they're not done yet.
ダメですよ
まだ できてないんですから
I'll use this to play with Sakamoto.
これで阪本と遊ぶ
（なの）あっ 猫じゃらしだ
Ah, a foxtail.
Sakamoto, Sakamoto.
（はかせ）阪本 阪本
Hey, kid, I've told you so many times to put "-san" after it!
（阪本）フンッ ちょっ ガキ！
あれほど “さん”を
つけろって言ってるだろ！
Ah, yeah. Sorry, Sakamoto.
あっ そうだった
ごめん　阪本
Are you making fun of me?
（阪本）
おちょくってんのか！
しまった つい うっかり
ごめんなさい　阪本
It happened unconsciously. Sorry, Sakamoto.
You're doing it on purpose, aren't you?!
（阪本）わざとだろ お前！
Well then, I'm going shopping!
（なの）
じゃあ 買い物行ってきまーす
Have a safe trip!
いってらっしゃーい
Seriously, the people here really haven't been educated, have they?
（阪本）まったく
本当に教育がなってないな
ここの連中は
I'm sorry, Sakamoto, I'm not doing it on purpose.
ごめん　阪本
わざとじゃないよ
I'm telling you, it's not Sakamoto!
（阪本）
だから 阪本じゃなくて！
Here, Sakamoto, I'll give you some gum.
はい　阪本　ガムあげるから
How many times are you going to make me say it!?
（阪本）何べん言わせるんだ！
Besides, have you ever heard of someone giving gum to a cat, you dumbas- Whoa!
しかも お前 猫にガム
あげるやつがあるかボケ！
（阪本）にゃあー！
（はかせ）アハハハハッ
（阪本）
にゃ にゃ にゃ にゃあー！
Cut it out already!
いいかげんにしろ！
I'm sorry.
ごめんなさい
Listen, I've told you before that I'm older than you two.
（阪本）いいか！
この前 言ったとおり―
お前らより 俺のほうが
年上なんだ
Adding "-san" when you address people older than you is...
目上の者にはきちんと
“さん”をつけて呼ぶのが…
I mean... that...
その… あれだ
In other words, it is...
いわゆる その…
It means that...
あれという… わけだ
So it means that...
つまり その…
あれというのは… だな
んんっ んん
（はかせ）あっ
（阪本）何だ！
Ah!
What is it?!
Can I go wee-wee?
おしっこ行っていいですか？
Ah, yeah, go ahead.
（阪本）はっ！ いいぞ
行ってこい！
（はかせ）
うん うん　おしっこ
Wee-wee!
You're taking it with you, huh?
（阪本）持っていくのかよ
From what I can see, there are only two kids living in this house.
見たところ―
やはり この家には
ガキ２人しか住んでいないようだ
I see.
なるほど
No wonder they're not educated.
教育がなっていないわけだ
Which means, I'm the oldest in this house.
…となると この家では
俺が最年長ということか
It can't be helped.
しょうがない
It'll be troublesome, but I'll act as their parent.
面倒だが やつらの
親代わりになってやるか
Seriously, I've been taken in by one hell of a house.
まったく 俺も とんでもない家に
拾われたもんだぜ
This is bad, yet it's so fun!
（阪本）やっべー！ 超楽しい！
Sakamoto, what are you doing?
（はかせ）阪本 何してるの？
（阪本）いっ？
This is bad,
（阪本）いかん
if she finds out that I was playing with the eraser,
消しゴムで遊んでたなんて
知られたら―
my place as parent will be...!
親としての威厳が…
My place as parent will...
威厳が…
My place as parent will be...
I might have slept for a bit.
ちょっと 寝てたかも
Cats sure do sleep a lot.
（はかせ）猫はいっぱい寝るな
Well, that's why.
（阪本）まあ そんなこんなでだ
That's why?
そんなこんなで？
Yeah, that's why.
（阪本）ああ そんなこんなで―
There are a lot of things lying around here, so...
いろいろ 詰め込んでも
あれだから
First off, shouldn't you start by apologising to your elders?
まずは 年上を敬うことから
始めようじゃ…
ないか！
This is bad, but it's really fun!
（阪本）やべえ  超楽しい！
（阪本）おっ！ はうわっ！
Whoa, Sakamoto, do it again, do it again!
（はかせ）わあっ！
阪本  もう一回 もう一回！
（はかせ）阪本
（阪本）いや 違う
Sakamoto!
N-No you're wrong, I was just...
Sakamoto, your leg!
（阪本）今のはだな
I mean, didn't I tell you to put "-san" after it?!
…つうか “さん”つけろって
言ってるだろうが
Sakamoto!
（なの）ただいま
（はかせ）ホームラーン！
I'm home!
Home run!
はいっ はいっ はいっ
Nakanojou
（中之条）えっ 母さーん！
（中之条の母）あああ！
Mother!
Nichijou 18
Daruma-san has...
（子ども）
だーるまさんが こーろんだ！
...tumbled down!
Daruma-san has...
だるーまさんが…
（祐子）あっ 麻衣ちゃん
また分かりにくいボケを
Mai-chan is doing her hard-to-get jokes again.
It can't be helped.
しょうがない
とりあえずツッコんどくか
For now, I'll take a jab at her.
Mai-chan, isn't that "on the book"?
麻衣ちゃん
それ オンザブックじゃん！
Yukko, don't ever try to take a jab at me like that again.
ゆっこ　二度と
そんなツッコミしないで
When you take such a good jab at me,
そんな いいツッコミされると―
it overshadows my funny man act.
私のボケが
かすんで見えちゃうから
ああ エッヘヘヘッ
No, it's that, you know?
いやあ あれだよ
I'm at the age where you start to unintentionally use English,
ついつい 英語が出ちゃう
年頃っつか なんつうか
I mean...
But you know, it was difficult to figure out if that "on the book" was serious or a joke.
でも そのオンザブック
素なのか ボケなのか―
分かりにくかったよ
Well, how do you call it, I just had to take a jab at it.
まあ なんつうか
性(さが)でツッコんだっつうか？
It was difficult to understand?
分かりにくい…
You're seriously saying that?
本気で そんなこと言ってるの？
It's because it's you.
（麻衣）これは ゆっこだから
（祐子）えっ？
Because it's you, I thought you'd understand.
（麻衣）ゆっこだから
分かってもらえると思って
わあっ アハハ
いやあ まいったね
No, I'm beat.
I didn't think you thought of me like that,
まさか そんなふうに
思われているとは
but I'm happy that you have faith in me.
でも 信用されてるっていうのは
うれしいなあ
Faith?
（麻衣）信用？
（祐子）ああ う… うん
Yeah...
We're not friends,
友達じゃないんだから
信用されるとか されないとか―
so can you stop talking about having or not having faith in you?
そういう話は やめてくれない？
Eh?
You don't need words between best friends, right?
親友に 言葉はいらないでしょ？
Mai... chan!
麻衣ちゃん
んもう 麻衣ちゃん！
Seriously, Mai-chan, it's okay to have a few words exchanged even between best friends, isn't it?
べつに 親友でも
言葉にしたっていいじゃんか
Mai... chan?
（祐子）麻衣… ちゃん？
If you're all over me like that, I'll be troubled.
あんまり ベタベタされると
困るんだけど
U-Um... sorry.
えっと
ごめん
ああ やめてよ
Stop it.
If you do that, I'll fall...
そんなことされたら
ゆっこのこと…
I'll fall even more in love with you.
（麻衣）ゆっこのこと…
より 好きになっちゃうから
い… いいじゃんか
好きになっちゃえば　ね？
It's okay to like me more, right?
We're best friends. Yo, best friend!
親友！ よっ 親友！
That's not the problem here.
（麻衣）
そういうんじゃ ないんだけど
We're not of the opposite sex, but it's kinda like I see you as one...
異性じゃないけど―
異性として
見ちゃうというか
（祐子）ガーン！
（麻衣）あっ ごめん
Sorry.
I can't say it... clearly.
ウマく 言えない
Ah... um...
W-What is this?!
Somehow, I thought she was a bit odd today.
なんか 今日
おかしいと思ったんだよ
You see, you see!
だってだって いつになく
結構しゃべるし―
She's talking more than usual.
She even said we should take a detour on the way home.
寄り道していこう
なんて言うし！
Was everything she did for the purpose of saying this?
全部 これ言うためだったの？
I mean... since when?
…ていうか いつから？
Since when did she start to feel that way?
いつから そういうのって
あっ ちょちょ ちょっと
まま… 麻衣ちゃん？
J-Just a second, M-Mai-chan...
あっ なな… 何ていうか その―
H-How do I put it, I-I'm not really sure about those things...
そういうのって
よく分かんないっていうか
I mean, it really is a bit too soon to say something like that.
やっぱり そういうのって
まだ 早いっていうか
I mean, we're still high schoolers after all!
まだ 高校生だからというか
That was a joke just now.
今の ボケたんだけど
Super ultra great delicious wonderful...
（祐子）スーパー ウルトラ
グレート デリシャス ワンダフル
...difficult to understand!
ワカリズレー！
Geez, stop putting on such weird acts.
もう！ 変な演技とかやめてよ
I sorta believed you for a moment there.
ちょっと
信じちゃったじゃんか！
I see.
（麻衣）そっか
（祐子）ええ？
Because it's you,
ゆっこだったら
頭の回転速いから―
and you're quick on the uptake, so I thought you'd understand.
分かってもらえると
思ったのに
ま… まあ
ちょっとは分かってたけど
Well, I did understand a little.
That's a lie, right?
ウソでしょ
No, no, it's not a lie or anything.
いやいや  ウソっていうか
何ていうか
It's like my head got the idea.
頭がピーンと働いたというか
Like, I really did understand it.
回転しちゃったというか
…てか 普通に考えたら―
Thinking about it, that was a weird conversation just now.
さっきの話自体
おかしいっていうか
Didn't you just say you believed it?
さっき 信じちゃったって
言わなかった？
I hate people who lie the most.
私 ウソつかれるの
一番嫌いなんだけど
Sorry.
ごめん
That was a joke too.
今のも ボケたんだけど
I can't tell if these are jokes or not any more!
（祐子）もう どこが何やら
気付きゃしないよ！
You didn't notice it?
気付かなかった？
ほかにも もう１つ
I had another one.
I don't know!
（祐子）分からないよ　どこ？
Which one is it?
When I said "you're quick on the uptake"...
“ゆっこは頭の回転が速い”
ってところ
...you were supposed to jab at it with "No, I'm not."
速くないよって
ツッコむところでしょ？
That one?!
（祐子）そこかあ！
However, that one is somehow very easy to understand.
でも そこだけ なんだか
とっても 分かりやすいよ
It's already been 40 years, this multi-unit apartment.
Try writing apartment wives.
You'll find an unbelievable degree of sexiness to it.
Next week's Nichijou is the fifth one.
Narration:      Obara Noriko
Look forward to it.
（団地）
もう 40年になります　団地です
“団地妻”って
書いてみてください
ほら すぐに とてつもない
お色気が  あんっ
次回の「日常」は
第５話
お楽しみに